My talk is going to be a little different. So my talk is going to be on a surprising
efficiency and exponential cost of fuzzing. So how can something be surprisingly efficient
and also come with an exponential cost? So the actual purpose of this talk is
to introduce to the weirdness of randomness and probability theory.
So given it - given a name of this event I won't talk much about the theory
but I want to talk about intuition. And one of the key messages that I want
you to take away from this talk is that we might have strong intuitions about solving a problem
but without a deep understanding of the problem sometimes our intuitions might lead us astray.
So what is fuzzing? Fuzzing is a testing process.
So here we are given a program and that program takes four characters.
One approach to test this program is called white box fuzzing - white box because the first
thing is that the analysis can actually see the internals of that program.
The program has four branches and we could now try to explore every path in
that program simply by trying to capture the conditions of each of these branches.
Say one branch is - one input would be exercising the path where the first character is not a b,
another input would exercise that path where the first input is a b but the second input
is not an a, and so on.
So we could explore all paths and at the end after exploring the fifth path - number
five - we would see that the program actually crashes.
And so in this sense this approach called white box fuzzing is actually most effective.
Why most effective? Because it can
actually prove the absence of an error, in this case of an assertion violation,
simply by enumerating all paths through the program.
Because you're making some assumptions but in principle we could say that white box buzzing
would be able to prove the absence of error, in this sense be most effective.
And also it's quite efficient,
so if we - suppose we are -
we have these five - there are five paths in that program.
If we sample a path at random without replacement we would expect to take about three inputs to find
that crashing bug, right,
generated by enumerating all of these paths using this technique called white box buzzing.
Now on the other side of the spectrum there's something called black box fuzzing.
Black box fuzzing doesn't know anything about the
program - what it would do - it simply generates random
inputs for that program. So in - on most machines a
character can take one of 256 values, and suppose we just randomly generate
these values using sampling - uniform at random with replacement.
Of course it can never prove the absence of errors,
in fact there's this great quote by Dijkstra saying program testing can
be used to show the presence of bugs but never too show their absence.
It's almost more recently we've looked into this problem of giving
testing some kind of statistical guarantees so we can somehow compute what is called a
residual risk after a certain amount of testing but the effect remains,
black box fuzzing is not most effective - it cannot prove the absence of errors.
Okay so then if we look at this from a statistical perspective,
I said earlier that white box fuzzing would require about three inputs and
expectation to find that bug. Now black box fuzzing,
if we sample each input each value for each character uniformly at random,
we would expect to generate about four billion inputs before
discovering this bug. This sounds a lot.
So then white box buzzing should be better, right, it's the most effective,
it's also quite efficient. And here it's where it's going
wrong for the first time, at least not always.
Sometimes black box fuzzing wins. And this was discovered 30-40
years ago when people started doing experiments with these two techniques
with the hypothetically most effective technique and with just a simple random sampling.
Somehow they found that given some limited time, this very simple, very dumb, technique wins and
finds more bugs than the most effective technique. And so we looked at this very recently
from a statistical perspective and found that if a white box
fuzzer takes too long per input our black box fuzzer outperforms the white box fuzzer.
Right, if the generation for one input takes
too long then the black box fuzzer outperforms. Because the black box fuzzer generates
inputs very fast. So on my machine it takes about 6.3
seconds to generate 4 billion inputs and if I had 100 machines
it would take 63 milliseconds so we can easily scale bug finding
because because black box fuzzing is essentially embarrassingly parallel.
And so in this paper we actually give a probabilistic bound on this maximum time.
So then is black box fuzzing the best that we can do?
And the answer here is wrong, not - we can do even better than that.
So what I presented here was a generational black box fuzzer.
What it means is, I generate
values for each of these characters, but I could also - instead of trying
to generate inputs from scratch, which is the generational approach,
maybe we can reuse existing inputs, and this is called mutational black box testing.
So suppose we have a seed input which is "bad?" The bad input is "bad!"
So if we had a mutational fuzzer which simply selects the four - which
simply selects the character at random and then chooses a value for that at random
then with a probability of one over four times one over 256
an expectation of about 1000 inputs which is much less than four billion inputs.
But I cheated a little bit here. We chose a really good seed to start with,
so can we do even better? Can we somehow automatically
discover this seed input? And this is where the
third approach gray box fuzzing comes in. Can we make can we take the advantage of black box
fuzzing and the advantage of white box fuzzing, can we kind of combine it?
And gray box fuzzing - because we don't actually analyze the program,
but we take some feedback called coverage feedback from gray box buzzing
and we add generated inputs to the corpus which increase coverage.
So suppose we just start with a random input. The probability that we generate the first
coverage increasing input is one over one thousand,
which means an expectation we require about 1024 inputs to
generate the first coverage increasing input. We add it to the corpus then we select this
next seed uniformly at random and in this case - this seed - and
the probability that we chose this seed, this character and generate 'a' as the value
requires about 2000 inputs. So we go on like that,
and easily starting from a random input we can generate - we can
find a bug using only 10,000 inputs. And now my machine just takes 150 microseconds.
So we - so this is much faster than a symbolic execution tool which requires
all this machinery - constraint solving and encoding and so on for three inputs.
And in the work that we presented at CCS16 we also boosted gray
box fuzzing simply by choosing that seed which exercises the lowest probability domain,
and we go down further to four thousand inputs and to 55 microseconds.
Okay so the insight is, if you have a really efficient fuzzer
let's just throw more machines at the problem. You remember on my machine it takes 6.3 seconds,
on 100 machines it takes 63 milliseconds to find the same bug.
So then you might think, well, if I have - I can
take X times small machines means I can find X times more bugs, right?
And again we are wrong. So this is an empirical cost.
We looked at a lot of data where we see this is an exponentially increasing number of machines.
It's a log scale here. And this is the number of additional
vulnerabilities discovered within the same time. And we see that on a linear increase in the number
of new vulnerabilities discovered requires an exponential increase in the number of machines.
And this is the exponential cost. And a little bit of an explanation here,
this is just the intuition. If you think about just one bug
and we increase the number of machines exponentially for a long time we won't -
for a long time means the number of machines - we won't see that bug
and there's almost linear increase at a certain number of machines
and then we are again almost - we have discovered this bug and so
we kind of go on with a straight line. If we now - instead of having just one
vulnerability we have 10 vulnerabilities we kind of get these quickly lines and
they almost look like straight lines and we increase the number of - the
number of vulnerabilities, number of bugs or whatever you want to measure you find it -
you get more and more linear. And the reason for this is that we have these
kind of constant - we never see that either - we never see the one to be discovered or we
always see the one already discovered and in between we have this
kind of almost linear increases. This is how we kind of get this linear
increase for an exponential number of machines. Okay so intuitively each new vulnerability
requires some more resources than the previous vulnerability
so the constant rate of vulnerability discovery requires exponential amount of resources.
So what I showed you is white box fuzzing - we have a technique which
we really love to work with, which is really smart,
which analyzes the program, which in fact is the most effective,
but in practice it is easily outperformed by a very dumb
technique called black box fuzzing, by simply randomly generating inputs.
And in fact this is so efficient that we can easily scale that across a lot
of machines and find the same the same number of bugs X times faster.
I also talked about a machine that kind of leverages the efficiency
of black box fuzzing but it's more like - but it enumerates paths like whitebox fuzzing
but then I explained how even that gray box fuzzing technique includes black box fuzzing
and gray box fuzzing are somehow affected by an exponential cost.
Thank you so much. All right thank you very much Marcel.
It's great to see this kind of quantitative approach to this problem.
A question coming in from one of the viewers is, how much of the statistics do I need to understand
to be able to apply these sorts of techniques? Oh so there's - that's - to apply it has no
need to understand statistics. It's more like - to understand
the statistics is more a help for you that - For instance, the insight that you cannot just
throw more machines at the problem and then hopefully you find more bugs, doesn't work.
At some point you kind of run out of machines because the cost for
finding more vulnerabilities is exponential. That's interesting to understand why this is the
case and we use statistics and probability theory to explain why this is the case.
But when you apply fuzzing you don't need to know, you don't need to know understand the statistics.
Maybe one other thing that we explored is that - we are often interested in the
probability that we find about - if we have not found a bug.
Suppose you have run a campaign for 24 hours and you have not found any bug,
You still want to know what is the probability that we find a
bug with just one more input generated and this is where you can use statistics.